Guide to the Samuel Bowles Papers
Yale University Library
- Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts
  - Bowles discusses in this unascribed letter the position of the Phelps suit against the Republican [copy], 1856
    - Thomas C. Zimmerman writes Schuyler Colfax asking him to write Bowles a letter on Professor William Evans, an eminent elocutionist. On the reverse side, Colfax recommends that Bowles follow Zimmerman's instructions on Evans., no date
  - Incomplete correspondence
    - An unsigned notation describes the ethics of the bar in the nineteenth century as leaving much to be desired., 1873 Sep 5
    - R. A. C. (unidentified) says to Bowles that if he examines the Republican platform for 1864 that he will find a plank or two on reform., 1874
    - The letter is unsigned and incomplete. The person is going abroad and shows a concern for national politics., n.y. Feb 27
    - Most of this letter is missing, and it is unsigned, although the handwriting is like that of Anna M. Tilcomb., Sunday
    - Lucy F. G. Writes Bowles a letter of thanks for their correspondence., no date
    - A fragment of a Bartlett letter is in the collection concerning his taking a seat in Washington., no date
    - A man with the initials H. J. G. acknowledges Bowles' letter and says that he may not be able to see Bowles in Boston., 1855 Aug 20
    - An unsigned poem on the theme"Flowers"is included., 1862 Jan 1
  - David Dudley Field correspondence
    - George Jones, newspaper publisher, believes Bowles has managed the Bowles-Field controversy with sagacity., 1870 Jan 21
    - Whitelaw Reid writes Bowles taking a stand close to that of Field, that one should be especially careful as to whether a suit is a libel or not. However, Reid would like to devote some columns to the publication of the Field letters. Reid thinks Bowles should make public any defamation in the character of David Dudley Field., 1871 Jan 25
    - Charles Dudley Warner congratulates Bowles; yet he points out that Field is smart. He expresses pride in Bowles as a journalist., 1871 Jan 25
    - Egbert Watson writes Bowles of knowing Field in childhood as one who was able to use his friends and associates., 1871 Jan 26
    - E. W. B. Canning, a townsman of Field, is in agreement with Bowles., 1871 Jan 27
    - W. W. Rice writes Bowles that he never knew such a correspondence as the Bowles-Field one to be profitable. Rice agrees with Bowles, but he thinks that Field's argument is plausible. He thinks that Bowles should look more into the legal profession., 1871 Jan 27
    - William Henry Brewer congratulates Bowles on his stand with Field and thinks that this point is often a problem of most professional people., 1871 Jan 28
    - Julius Hawley Seelye is in sympathy with Bowles; he suggests that the question is not "whether a villain should always berefusedfor a client, but whether his villainy should be held up as not heinous and as worthy of the solemn approval of justice.", 1871 Jan 28
    - Whitelaw Reid reports to Bowles that he was unable to superviseprintingof the Field material but thanks Bowles for the power of justice., 1871 Jan 29
    - Dawes congratulates Bowles on his management of the Bowles-Field controversy and is glad that Bowles did not enter a technical argument with Field., 1871 Jan 30
    - Schluemback congratulates Bowles on the liberating quality of the Field correspondence., 1871 Jan 30
    - William A. Seaver congratulates Bowles on his justice and ability in the Field-Bowles controversy., 1871 Jan 30
    - W. A. Steasul writes Bowles a congratulatory note on the Field affair., 1871 Jan 30
    - G. Boutwell states he believes that the Fields are "worsted" in the encounter of Bowles-Field., 1871 Jan 31
    - C. C. Chaffee writes a congratulatory note to Bowles on the Field case., 1871 Jan 31
    - R. Hawkins agrees with Bowles on the Field case., 1871 Jan 31
    - James Reed Spalding writes a congratulatory note to Bowles on his stand with Field., 1871 Feb 10
    - C. A. Runkle is pleased with Bowles' stand against Field; however, he wishes that he had gonefurtherin the bribery question., 1871 Jan 31
    - George Walker writes Bowles a congratulatory letter on his stand in the Field affair., 1871 Jan 31
    - An anonymous letter reports on what a fellow passenger on a train said of Field with the indication that Bowles should have pressed more., 1871 Jan 31
    - Bowles receives an unsigned congratulatory note on the Bowles-Field correspondence., 1871 Jan 31
    - John Rogers writes David Dudley Field accusing him of collaboration with Judge Barnard., 1871 Feb 1
    - S. Sheaven writes a congratulatory letter to Bowles., 1871 Feb 2
    - Charles Dudley Warnerpointsout to Bowles that he has caused quite a row. Warner discusses the affair with some agreement with Bowles., 1871 Feb 2
    - Gardner L., who knew Field in his youth, congratulates Bowles., 1871 Feb 3
    - P. M. Reed, a lawyer from Old Lyme, writes Bowles that he regards Field's position as untenable and wrong., 1871 Feb 4
    - Edwin M. Stone expresses interest in the moralissue of the Field controversy., 1871 Feb 4
    - Washington Gladden writes Bowles that he is in agreement with him on his stand in the Field affair. Gladden wrote an article for the NY Independent on the subject., 1871 Feb 6
    - Charles Rice sends a complimentary letter to Bowles for his stand with Field., 1871 Feb 6
    - Charles John Reed brings out the point to Bowles that Fisk and Gould have the right to be defended by law., 1871 Feb 7
    - Alexander Hyde thanks Bowles for the favor to the journalistic profession., 1871 Feb 10
    - Charles Allen writes Bowles that a case can be so dishonest that a lawyer will suffer if he tries it in court., 1871 Feb 13
    - C. H. Muff is in agreement with Bowles on the Field correspondence., 1871 Feb 13
    - Samuel Wolcott praises Bowles for his stand on the moral issue in the Bowles-Field controversy., 1871 Feb 13
    - Bigelow writes Bowles that the D. D. Field affair should have been exposed long before and is sorry that New York couldn't have done it., 1871 Feb 22
    - C. F. Adams, Jr., writes Bowles that he thinks that Field received very little from Bowles and that Bowles' correspondence was the least he should have had., 1871 Feb 27
    - Lewis B. Parsues is pleased with Bowles' stand in the Bowles-Field controversy., 1875 Feb 5
    - Billings writes Bowles a congratulatory letter on the Field case., n.y., n.m. 24
    - A scrap of paper from George P. Rand was found in the Field correspondence.
    - A list of the Field correspondence is enclosed in the collection - probably made by Bowles.
    - The Lawyer and His Clients
    - The Duties and Rights of Counsel
  - Mayoralty contest of 1873
    - Walker tells Bowles that perhaps he is right in not running for mayor., 1874 Mar 17
    - Clark W. Bryan writes Bowles admiring him for his stand in not running for mayor., 1873 Nov 15
    - A letter from George Walker to Bowles urges him to run for mayor., 1873 Nov 15
    - A letter from Herbert Lawrence Bridgman congratulates Bowles on his stand as to the election for mayor in Springfield., 1873 Nov 17
    - Alexander H. Bullock discussed an invitation to dine at a club in Springfield with Bowles and other Springfield men., 1873 Nov 19
    - E. B. Gillette regrets that Bowles will not run for mayor., 1873
    - The collection contains nineteen newspaper clippings on Bowles' stand in the mayoralty contest.
    - A petition is drawn up by the citizens of Springfield, urging Bowles to run for mayor.
  - The New York jail episode
    - Edm. C. Dwight expresses regret that Bowles was treated in such a way but suggests that the incident brought out the worst of the accused., 1868 Dec 20
    - Henry Martyn Field expresses his rage over Bowles being seized., 1868 Dec 23
    - Henry Wilson Corbett expresses disgust at the way Bowles has been treated and hopes that Bowles will vindicate himself by exposing them., 1868 Dec 23
    - Robert Bonner expresses unhappiness over the dishonor done Bowles in the jail episode., 1868 Dec 24
    - Joseph Roswell Hawley expresses delight that now Bowles can see how many friends he has, although he is unhappy with his being put in jail., 1868 Dec 24
    - J. P. Putnam writes a letter expressing his outrage at Bowles having been jailed., 1868 Dec 24
    - William Augustus Stearns acknowledges that the treatment of Bowles by Fisk was dastardly., 1868 Dec 26
    - Thomas Russell gives Bowles an invitation to dine with a number of outstanding people who want to attest to Bowles' character., 1868 Dec 27
    - John Pierce jokingly discusses Bowles writing a book on his prison experiences. The letter takes advantage of Bowles having been in jail. It begins, "Dear Jailbird." Pierce advises Bowles to quit attacking people in his pages., 1868 Dec 28
    - Donald Grant Mitchell (Ik Marvel) expresses indignation at Bowles' treatment in New York., [1868?]
    - A brochure is contained in this packet with a group of names of people who want to honor the character of Bowles.
  - The Death of Samuel Bowles
    - George W. Smalley is distressed to hear that Bowles is ill and suggests that he go to Europe., 1877 Nov 20
    - Musgrave writes Bowles of a letter received from Halstead. He wants to keep posted on Bowles' improvement., 1877 Nov 30
    - M. E. B. (not identified) hopes the change of weather will not bring ill effects to Bowles., 1877 Dec 1
    - E. B. Haskell has heard of Bowles' ill health and says that nature must fit him with a perishable casket., 1877 Dec 3
    - James A. Briggs expresses happiness at hearing of Bowles' improvement., 1877 Dec 17
    - Joseph Pulitzer expresses sorrow at Bowles' illness and delight at his seeming recovery., 1877 Dec 20
    - James D. Colt says any man who can express views on the senatorial contest must be well on the way to recovery. He is happy that Bowles has taken a turn for the best., 1877 Dec 21
    - J. M. Dalgell sends heartfelt joy at Bowles' restoration to partial health., 1877 Dec 22
    - Henry Cooley had called at Bowles' office and was informed of his illness. His point was to tell Bowles that he had come into harmony with his views and felt that the Republican had followed the right course., 1877 Dec 24
    - William Orton tells Bowles that he has read of his severe illness and expresses desire for his complete recovery., 1877 Dec 27
    - J. Brady writes Bowles that nothing except duties to be performed prevent him from going to see Bowles with Musgrave., 1877
    - Weir Mitchell prescribes a certain beer for Bowles. He is happy to hear of Bowles' gain in health., 1877
    - Benjamin F. Bowles hopes that his note is no intrusion; however, he says that though they differ politically, he thinks that it would be a pity if he could not express his bereavement., 1878 Jan 7
  - Letters to Mary Bowles on the death of Samuel Bowles II. The following letters express sympathy to Mrs. Bowles on the illness and death of her husband; they will be listed by date and writer only.
    - Carl Schurz, 1873 Dec 19
    - Martha Goddard, 1877 Nov 21
    - E. W. B. Channing, 1877 Dec 4
    - Schuyler Colfax, 1877 Dec 4
    - T. T. Lindley, 1877 Dec 4
    - Henry Martyn Field, 1877 Dec 11
    - Carl Schurz, 1878 Jan 9
    - Joseph Gilbert Holland, 1878 Jan 15
    - Washington Gladden, 1878 Jan 17
    - William Bross, 1878 Jan 18
    - Carl Schurz, 1878 Jan 18
    - Henry Laurens Dawes, 1878 Jan 19
    - Richard Salter Storrs, 1878 Jan 22
    - Isabella Bird, 1878 Jan 23
    - Martha Goddard, 1878 Jan 25
    - Henry George Stebbins, 1878 Feb 1
    - Cyrus West Field, 1890 Dec 8
    - Henry Laurens Dawes, 1893 Apr 8
    - A newspaper account of Bowles' death is also included in Mrs. Bowles' papers.
  - Letters to Samuel Bowles III (1851-1915) on the death of Samuel Bowles II. The following letters express sympathy to Samuel Bowles on the illness and death of his father. They are listed by date and writer only.
    - D. W. Boutwell, 1877 Dec 3
    - Ames L. Learner, 1877 Dec 4
    - William Walter Phelps, 1877 Dec 4
    - R. W. Pomeroy, 1877 Dec 4
    - Henry Warner, 1877 Dec 4
    - Edward Heaton, 1877 Dec 5
    - Mary Clemmer, 1877 Dec 6
    - Murat Halstead, 1877 Dec 6
    - Weir Mitchell, 1877 Dec 6
    - C. W. Willard, 1877 Dec 6
    - Fordyce Barker, 1877 Dec 10
    - J. L. Jenkins, 1877 Dec 11
    - Murdock Billings, 1877 Dec 13
    - H. L. Bridfruary, 1877 Dec 13
    - Musgrave, 1877 Dec 13
    - Robert Pomeroy, 1877 Dec 14
    - Washington Gladden, 1877 Dec 20
    - B. H. Bristow, 1877 Dec 23
    - H. L. Dawes, 1877 Dec 23
    - Musgrave, 1877 Dec 24
    - T. B. Musgrave, 1877 Dec 25
    - Carl Schurz, 1877 Dec 26
    - Carl Schurz, 1877 Dec 31
    - Fordyce Barker, 1877
    - Griffin, 1877
    - Jenny Warner, 1878 Jan 1
    - R. W. Pomeroy, 1878 Jan 2
    - Musgrave, 1878 Jan 12
    - Robert Pomeroy, 1878 Jan 12
    - C. Allen, 1878 Jan 14
    - T. B. Musgrave, 1878 Jan 16
    - James L. Whitney, 1878 Jan 16
    - Frederick Billings, 1878 Jan 17
    - D. W. Boutwell, 1878 Jan 17
    - Sidney Dickinson, 1878 Jan 17
    - Murat Halstead, 1878 Jan 17
    - W. Pomeroy, 1878 Jan 17
    - George B. Smith, 1878 Jan 18
    - H. L. Bridsman, 1878 Jan 19
    - Robert Pomeroy, 1878 Jan 19
    - Edward P. Albee, 1878 Jan 20
    - D. W. Bartlett, 1878 Jan 20
    - Fordyce Barker, 1878 Jan 21
    - Noah Brooks, 1878 Jan 21
    - S. S. Conant, 1878 Jan 21
    - C. R. Miller, 1878 Jan 21
    - Charles Francis Adams, Jr., 1878 Jan 22
    - Frederick Billings, 1878 Jan 22
    - N. D. Bond, 1878 Jan 22
    - Frank T. Bowles, 1878 Jan 22
    - A. G. Browne, 1878 Jan 22
    - D. A. Goddard, 1878 Jan 22
    - D. D. Hubbard, 1878 Jan 22
    - Marshall Jewell, 1878 Jan 22
    - C. J. Morrill, 1878 Jan 22
    - Jenny Warner, 1878 Jan 22
    - Walter Allen, 1878 Jan 23
    - H. M. Clarke, 1878 Jan 23
    - Henry Cabot Lodge, 1878 Jan 23
    - Murat Halstead, 1878 Jan 25
    - Richard Henry Dana, Jr., 1878 Jan 27
    - Murat Halstead, 1878 Jan
  - Miscellaneous material on the death of Samuel Bowles
    - A letter to a Mrs. Leonard from M. Noylad says that he does not know any of the family except the father; yet he hopes someone will express his feelings to them., 1877 Dec 5
    - A letter from H. D. Lloyd to Miss Titcomb tells of some things that might be done to save Bowles' life., 1877 Dec 6
    - Charles Nordhoff writes a Miss Clark that he has word that Bowles is somewhat better. He gives information on the president as being firm against powerfully combined forces., 1877 Dec 19
    - Charles D. Warner tells E. F. Hayes that he had planned to be present at the funeral itself until announced that it was private., 1878 Jan 19
    - A letter addressed to no one, signed with theinitialsA. P. L., laments the death of Samuel Bowles II., 1878 Jan 19
    - Isaac H. Brosseler writes E. F. Hayes that he shall be present at the memorial service., 1878 Jan 20
    - A letter to E. F. Hayes from Hooker says that he shall have to be in attendance upon the Supreme Court of Bridgeport, and he is very sad that he cannot attend the funeral., 1878 Jan 20
    - Berry H. Bailey writes a letter to the publishers of the Republican enclosing a money order for his subscription for a year; he also wants the issue on Bowles' death., 1878 Jan 21
    - Four announcements of Bowles' memorial service are in this collection. There are four programs from the memorial service. Some calling cards to Bowles during his illness are included. There are two copies of the Charles Dudley Warner reading at the memorial service. An appreciation from the city of Springfield for Samuel Bowles II is in the collection.
  - Miscellaneous material
    - Two copies of the first issues of the Republican
    - News article "How Jeff Davis Escaped Prosecution for Treason"
    - A memorial pamphlet on Howard Parmelee Ellis, 1855-1919
    - A partial newspaper article on the death of Samuel Bowles, III
    - Pamphlet on the Bowles-Phelps Suit
    - Two copies of a newspaper article, "The Moral Limits of Professional Service," were included in this packet of letters.
    - A newspaper article is contained in this packet concerning the marriage of the eldest daughter of Cyrus W. Field. A second article also appears on this subject.
    - The Travelers Record is included with a tribute to Samuel Bowles on his pending death.
    - A clipping concerning the Beecher trial is included.
    - A newspaper article on Lessie Goodell Gustafson appears in this section.
    - A large group of petitioners desire Bowles to dine with them due to respect for his character. This letter contains a petition. (missing 2/1/79), 1868 Dec 24
    - A receipt of Mrs. Bowles for Kelsey and Allen - purchase of soap - is in the collection., 1883 Oct 3
    - Fourteen copies of printed correspondence to the director of the Boston and Chicago Gold Mining Co. offering stock for sale are included in the collection.
    - The program for a complimentary reception to Schuyler Colfax and friends is in the collection., 1865 Aug 31
    - A trust calling for the organization of a new party is included in this Bowles packet. A meeting is to be held in Worcester in December. Among the signatories are Samuel Hooker, Charles Francis Adams, Sr., George Boutwell, George Bliss, H. L. Dawes, and Samuel Bowles., 1855
    - Printed request forSamuelBowles to be the guest of honor at a dinner attesting to his character and Bowles' declination of the event are in the collection., 1868
    - Copy of the New York Supreme Court case between Mary S. D. Bowles and John S. Prouty
    - Three copies of the Phelps-Bowles correspondence
    - Six Chinese companies in San Francisco, California, invite Samuel Bowles, Schuyler Colfax, William Bross, and Albert D. Richardson to a complimentary dinner., 1865 Aug 15
    - A statement of the Republica n letters appointing Bowles to deliver a trust to the President of the Senate, among the signatures are those of Robert C. Winthrop, George Bliss, and Rufus Bullock., 1855 Jan
    - Two menus for a complimentary dinner given for Samuel Bowles at Springfield, 1857 Apr 18
    - A list of names and an Alfred A. Jessup calling card are in the collection.
    - "Fra Giacana," a poem by R. Buchanan is in this section.
    - Three law pamphlets were found in packets in this part of the collection: The Lawyer: The Dignity, Duties, and Responsibilities of His Profession, Richard Burleigh Kimball; Law and Lawyers, Matthew Paul Drady; An Address to His Law Students, John Worth Edmonds (all three pamphlets are missing 2/1/79)